Finding Aid for Eliza Jane Read Sunderland papers 1865-1910
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eliza Jane Read Sunderland Papers 1865-1910
Sunderland, Eliza Read, 1839-1910.
86201 Aa 2
Lecturer, educator, author and advocate of women's rights during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, received Ph.D. in Philosophy from University of Michigan in 1892 under supervision of John Dewey. Papers include correspondence, some with Dewey and other leading philosophers, her student notebooks, articles, lectures and sermons.
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the Sunderlands' granddaughter, Mrs. Harold Wethey (Donor no. 3061 ) and came to the library in 1972. Smaller accessions have been received from her since then. A small amount of material was received form a great-granddaughter of the Sunderland's, Janet Toohy Ferguson (Donor no. 9192 ) in 2002.
The collection is open for research.
Portions of the Eliza Read Sunderland papers have been microfilmed and are available through inter-library loan. The microfilmed material, principally her student notebooks for course taught by John Dewey, is annotated in the contents list.
Eliza Jane Read Sunderland was a lecturer, educator, author and advocate of women's rights during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. A native of Huntsville, Illinois, she graduated from Mount Holyoke Seminary in Massachusetts in 1865. After declining an offer to teach at Mount Holyoke, she returned to Illinois to become a teacher at Aurora High School. She soon became principal of this school, serving in this position for four years.
She left Aurora in 1871, upon her marriage to Unitarian clergyman Jabez T. Sunderland, but continued to teach in the various towns where he was a minister. During the 1880s, when her husband was the minister of the First Unitarian Church of Ann Arbor, Mrs. Sunderland entered the University of Michigan. Here she received her B.A. degree in 1889 and her doctorate in philosophy in 1892. Sunderland was one of the earliest women to receive a doctorate from the University of Michigan. Her thesis entitled "Man's Relation to the Absolute According to Kant and Hegel" was written under the supervision of Professor John Dewey.
Sunderland was an exceptional woman not only for the level of her education but also for the career that she made for herself. Unlike most churches in the nineteenth century, the Unitarian Church allowed women to enter the ministry. Although she never became a minister, Sunderland often took her husband's place in the pulpit as well as giving guest sermons in other Unitarian Churches. She was also an editor besides writing extensively for literary and religious papers and magazines of the day. And she was involved in different women's organizations. From 1886 to 1895, she served on the National Board of the Association for the Advancement of Women. In 1893, she served as one of the main speakers at the Women's Congress of the World's Columbian Exposition, and in 1907, she was elected to the school board in Hartford, Connecticut, becoming the first women to serve on that body.
Eliza Read Sunderland died March 3, 1910 in Hartford, Connecticut where she had moved in 1906.
The collection, covering the period of 1865 to 1910, has been arranged into five series:
Correspondence, 1865-1910 (bulk 1890-1910)
Biographical/Writings, 1878 to 1903
Notebooks, ca. 1884-1897
Articles, Lectures, and Sermons
Collected Articles and Clippings, ca 1878-1910
The Eliza Jane Read Sunderland papers document through correspondence, articles, sermons, and other materials the active life of an advocate of woman's rights during the last decades of the nineteenth century and the first decade of the twentieth.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Education--United States.; Scott, Fred Newton, 1860-1931.; Sunderland, Eliza Read, 1839-1910.; Tufts, James Hayden, 1862-1942.; Unitarian churches.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.; Women--Suffrage--Michigan.; Women's rights--Michigan.; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.)
Contributors:
Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Association for the Advancement of Women.; Chapin, Augusta J., d. 1905.; Collyer, Robert, 1823-1912.; Connecticut Woman Suffrage Association.; Crane, Caroline Bartlett, 1858-1935.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Eliot, Samuel Atkins, 1862-1950.; Gannett, William C. (William Channing), 1840-1923.; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909.; Howe, Julia Ward, 1819-1910.; Jones, Jenkin Lloyd, 1843-1918.; Jordan, Myra Beach, 1863-1946.; Michigan Equal Suffrage Association.; Michigan State Federation of Women's Clubs.; National Alliance of Unitarian and other Liberal Christian Women.; Stone, Lucinda Hinsdale, 1814-1900.; Women's Western Unitarian Conference.
Genre/Form:
Sermons.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series covers the period of 1865 to 1910, though it bulks largest for the period since 1880. This series is especially rich as it includes correspondence with faculty members at the University of Michigan, notably John Dewey, Henry Carter Adams, and President James B. Angell. Eliza Sunderland also corresponded with prominent figures in the Unitarian Church, individuals such as Augusta Chapin, Robert Collyer, Samuel A. Eliot, William C. Gannett, Edward Hale, and Jenkin Lloyd Jones. From her involvement with the Association for the Advancement of Women, Sunderland received a number of letters from Julia Ward Howe and other officers of the organization. At various times, she also corresponded with Caroline Bartlett Crane, Myra B. Jordan, Lucinda H. Stone, the Connecticut Woman Suffrage Association, the Michigan Equal Suffrage Association, and the Michigan State Federation of Women's Clubs. Researchers interested in Sunderland's family concerns may also wish to view the Sunderland-Safford family papers which include Sunderland's letters to her daughter, Bertrude Safford-Sunderland.
  - Undated 1865-1910, 36 folders (Box 1)
- Biographical/Writings
  The Biographical/Writings series consists of biographical information about Sunderland, also published copies of various pamphlets and articles authored by her. These date in the period of 1878 to 1903.
  - Biographical material, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and articles by Mrs. Sunderland 1878-1903, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Notebooks
  The Notebooks series has two subseries. The most extensive of these is a run of notebooks compiled by Sunderland while a student at the University of Michigan in the early 1890s. Most of these are for philosophy courses taught by John Dewey. There are also notes for other classes taught by Fred Newton Scott, James Tufts, and Henry Carter Adams. The other subseries - labeled as "Various" - includes notes taken while traveling in Europe and a diary of a trip to England in 1895.
  - University of Michigan student notebooks (Box 2)
    - Introduction to Philosophy course taught by John Dewey 1890 (Box 2)
      (microfilm copy available: mf 622c)
    - Aesthetics course taught by Fred N. Scott 1890 (Box 2)
    - Real Logic course taught by John Dewey 1890 (Box 2)
    - Kant's Critique of Pure Reason and Caird's Critical Philosophy of Kant courses taught by John Dewey 1890 (Box 2)
    - Studies in the History and Philosophy of Religion course taught by James H., Tufts 1891 (Box 2)
    - Hegel's logic course taught by John Dewey 1891 (Box 2)
    - Hegel's Philosophy of Spirit course taught by John Dewey 1891 (Box 2)
    - Social and Industrial Reforms course taught by Henry Carter Adams 1891 (Box 2)
    - Movements of Thought in the Nineteenth Century 1891 taught by John Dewey, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - Ethical Problems seminar taught by John Dewey circa 1892 (Box 2)
    - Notebook contains seminar papers on Herbert Spencer's Psychology 1882 and Berkley's Principles of Human Knowledge, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Various
    - Rough draft of Sunderland's PhD. thesis, undated (Box 2)
    - Notes on Rome, undated (Box 2)
    - Notes on Italy and Robert Burns, undated (Box 2)
    - Account book of household income and expenditures 1884-1894 (Box 2)
      (volume includes American history test questions in 1883)
    - Diary of trip to England 1895 (Box 2)
      (volume also includes accounts for 1896-1897)
- Articles, Lectures and Sermons
  The largest series within the collection comprises the numerous Articles, Lectures, and Sermons given by Sunderland throughout her life. These have been arranged into two subseries: titles arranged alphabetically, and titles arranged chronologically (when that date is known). Many of these papers were given from Unitarian pulpits. Although many have religious themes, there are also a number that concern women's rights, the education of women, and women's issues in general. The sermons with dates span the years 1874 to 1909.
  - Alphabetical by title
    - After Vacation, What? (Box 2)
    - Agnosticism (Box 2)
    - Agnosticism: A Historical and Practical Study (Box 2)
    - An Analysis of Jastro's "The Subconscious" (Box 2)
    - Books and Reading for Children Young and Old (Box 2)
    - Christian Art (Box 2)
    - Christianity Since Jesus (Box 2)
    - The Comparative Value of the Pulpit and the Press as a Means of Liberal Religious Propaganda (Box 2)
    - Conversion of the Barbarians (Box 2)
    - The Cross of Christ (Box 2)
    - The Duty of Patriotic Citizens in Time of War (Box 2)
    - Early American Literature (Box 2)
    - Early Beginnings of American Unitarianism (Box 2)
    - Education, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - The Educational Work of Women's Clubs (Box 3)
    - The Effects of the Reformation on Philosophy and Science (Box 3)
    - England at Play (Box 3)
    - England at School (Box 3)
    - The First Seven Years of the Child's Life (Box 3)
    - The Foundations of Religion (Box 3)
    - Herman Lotze (Box 3)
    - The High Church Movement (Box 3)
    - The Higher Education of Women (Box 3)
    - The History of Music (Box 3)
    - How Can We Know God? (Box 3)
    - The Influence of Religion Upon Fine Art (Box 3)
    - The Inspiration of the Vir (?) and of the Home (Box 3)
    - The Jewish Messiah (Box 3)
    - Longfellow (Box 3)
    - Man: His Origin, Destiny, and End (Box 3)
    - Medieval Universities (Box 3)
    - The New Basis of Civilization (Box 3)
    - New Testament Criticism of the Nineteenth Century (Box 3)
    - A New Year's Sermon on the Past, Present, and Future of Christianity (Box 3)
    - Old World Art in New World Life (Box 3)
    - Our Father Who Art in Heaven (Box 3)
    - Our Modern Sale of Indulgence (Box 3)
    - The Protective Tariff (Box 3)
    - Religion in Italy (Box 3)
    - Schopenhauer and Steiner (Box 3)
    - Some Religious Teachings of Emerson (Box 3)
    - The Soul (Box 3)
    - Studies in the Life of Jesus, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Victor Hugo (Box 3)
    - Vocations and Avocations for Women (Box 3)
    - What is the Bible? (Box 3)
    - Whereesoever This Gospel Shall Be Preached ... There Shall Also This That His Women Hath Done, Be Told for a Memorial of Her (Box 3)
    - Will Education Destroy Intemperance? (Box 3)
    - William Wordsworth (Box 3)
    - Wise and Foolish Virgins in Gothic Cathedrals (Box 3)
    - Woman as an Economic Factor in the American Life (Box 3)
    - The World Waits Upon the Babe (Box 3)
  - Arranged by date
    - 1874
      - The Book (Box 3)
    - 1880
      - Lucretia Mott (Box 3)
    - 1881
      - The Attitude of the Great Religions of the World Toward Women (Box 3)
    - 1882
      - Dr. J.G. Holland (Box 3)
    - 1885
      - History of Unitarianism (Box 3)
      - The Study of Religious Literature as an Essential Part of Church Work (Box 3)
      - The Secret of Success in Life (Box 3)
      - The Problem of Life (Box 3)
      - Where is thy Brother (Box 3)
      - Bear Ye One Another's Burdens (Box 3)
      - The Everlasting Gospel (Box 3)
    - 1888
      - Parasites (Box 3)
    - 1889
      - What Has Jesus Done for the World (Box 3)
    - 1890
      - A Christmas Sermon (Box 3)
    - 1892
      - The Essence of Unitarian Christianity (Box 3)
      - In Memoriam (Box 3)
      - Scientific Truth and Religious Truth (Box 3)
    - circa 1892
      - Man's Relation to the Absolute According to the Philosophy of Kant and of Hegel (Box 3)
    - 1893
      - The Higher Education of Women and Its Influence on the Home Life (Box 3)
      - Importance of the Study of Comparative Religion (Box 4)
    - 1894
      - Lost Paradises (Box 4)
      - The Religious Field (Box 4)
      - The Historic Resurrection and the Real Resurrection (Box 4)
      - Old Testament Biblical Criticism (Box 4)
      - Immanuel Kant (Box 4)
      - Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel (Box 4)
      - Arthur Schopenhauer and Karl Robert Edward Von Hartmann (Box 4)
      - August Comte (Box 4)
      - John Stuart Mill and Herbert Spencer (Box 4)
      - James Martineau (Box 4)
      - The Scientists (Box 4)
    - 1895
      - Thomas Carlyle's House (Box 4)
    - 1896
      - Immortality (Box 4)
      - Paul on Mars Hill (Box 4)
      - Three Stories of Creation (Box 4)
    - 1897
      - Salvation (Box 4)
      - Elements Which Enter into the Making of a Great Soul (Box 4)
      - The Way of Salvation (Box 4)
      - The Secret of Jesus (Box 4)
    - 1898
      - Some Things Worth Living For (Box 4)
    - 1905
      - Righteousness (Box 4)
    - circa 1908
      - Political speech (Box 4)
      - Right and Wrong Uses of the Bible in Sunday School (Box 4)
    - 1908
      - Henrik Ibsen (Box 4)
    - circa 1909
      - A Study of the American Public School System (Box 4)
    - 1909
      - Some Reasons Why Women Should Have the Ballot (Box 4)
      - The Great Choice (Box 4)
      - The Growing Boy (Box 4)
      - The Making of the Man (Box 4)
      - Teaching and Healing (Box 4)
      - The Infancy Legends (Box 4)
- Collected Articles and Clippings Files
  The Collected Articles and Clippings series consists of subject files relating to women and women's organizations, the education of women, and the condition of working women. This series also includes obituary notices of Sunderland following her death in 1910, and autograph/guest book Sunderland kept, with entries form 1890-1897.
  - Women and women's organizations undated (Box 4)
  - Women and women's organizations 1878-1899 (Box 4)
  - Women and women's organizations 1900-1909 (Box 4)
  - Working women 1879-1898, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Higher Education of Women and the Association of Collegiate Alumnae 1882-1897, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - World's Congress of Representative Women 1893 (Box 4)
  - Activities of Eliza Sunderland 1877-1903 (Box 4)
  - Obituaries of Eliza Sunderland 1910 (Box 4)
  - Notes on William Ewart Gladstone (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Autograph Book 1890-1897 (Box 4)
Partial Index to Correspondence
Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.
Nov. 20, 1890
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.
June 19, June 23, Nov. 12, 1888, July 4, 1895
Association for the Advancement of Women
1886, 1887, 1890, 1891
Chapin, Augusta J., d. 1905.
Oct. 26, 1882, Feb. 2, 1885, Aug. 6, Aug. 16, 1893, Sept. 5, 1893
Collyer, Robert, 1823-1912.
Jan. 24, 1878, Aug. 23, 1881
Connecticut Woman Suffrage Association
1908, 1909
Crane, Caroline Bartlett, 1858-1935.
Mar. 26, 1894, Jan. 8, 1902
Dewey, John, 1859-1952.
June 23, 1894
Eliot, Samuel Atkins, 1862-1950.
Mar. 22, 1905
Gannett, William Channing, 1840-1923.
Oct. 27, 1881, Oct. 11, 1882, Mar. 21, 1885
Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909.
Feb. 4, 1884, May 22, 1884
Howe, Julia Ward, 1819-1910.
Nov. 25, 1883, Mar. 2, Sept. 6, 1887, Aug. 20, 1888
Jones, Jenkin Lloyd, 1843-1918.
Oct. 7, 1881
Jordan, Myra Beach, 1863-1946.
1892, Feb. 21, 1896, 1899 undated
Michigan Equal Suffrage Association
Jan. 5, 1887, Apr. 11, 1891, Mar. 12, Dec. 2, 1892
Michigan State Federation of Women's Clubs.
1897, 1898
National Alliance of Unitarian and Other Liberal Christian Women
1892, 1893, 1894, 1897, 1908, 1909
Stone, Lucinda Hinsdale, 1814-1900.
Sept. 28, Oct. 15, Oct. 25, 1891
Women's Western Unitarian Conference
1882, 1886